{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man advocated for a “priesthood of all believers” in the work To the Christian Nobility of the\nGerman Nation. He was protected by Frederick the Wise after Charles V ordered his arrest. Pope Leo X\nexcommunicated this man with the bull Exsurge Domine [EX-ur-gay DOE-mee-nay] after he posted the\n95 Theses. For ten points, name this German priest who began the Protestant Reformation.",
      "answer": [
        "Martin Luther",
        "Luther"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This nation was invaded by Huang Taiji in 1636 as the Qing [CHING] dynasty sought to solidify its\nwar against the Ming. In 1592, Toyotomi Hideyoshi’s invasion of this nation was disrupted by enemy turtle\nships. The Joseon dynasty ruled it until 1897, and it was annexed by Japan in 1910. For ten points, name\nthis East Asian peninsula split after World War II by Soviet and American agreement into two countries\nwith capitals Pyongyang and Seoul.",
      "answer": [
        "Korean Peninsula",
        "Korea"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Shoshone [sho-sho-nay] Falls and Twin Falls lie on this river, whose largest tributary is the Salmon\nRiver. In 1974, Evel Knievel’s Skycycle X-2 nearly jumped a canyon of this tributary of the Columbia\nRiver. For ten points, name this river that flows through Hells Canyon after receiving the Boise River\nnear the border of Oregon and Idaho.",
      "answer": [
        "Snake River",
        "Snake"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The rVSV-ZEBOV vaccine has been shown effective in treating this disease. Emile Ouamouno died six\ndays after contracting this disease, and Eric Duncan infected two Americans with it. Liberia was declared\nfree of this disease after 42 days with no new cases. For ten points, name this disease which caused a 2014\nepidemic in West Africa.",
      "answer": [
        "Ebola virus disease",
        "Ebola",
        "Ebola hemorrhagic fever"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In the Hellenistic period, this deity was syncretized with Apis to form the god Serapis. The djed pillar\nrepresented the spine of this deity, whose wife searched throughout Egypt to find the 14 pieces of his body\nafter he was torn apart by his jealous brother, Set. For ten points, name this Egyptian god of the afterlife\nwhose consort was his sister, Isis.",
      "answer": "Osiris"
    },
    {
      "question": "This president’s “New Look” policy led to the overthrow of Guatemalan Jacobo Arbenz. This\npresident overhauled the nation’s infrastructure with the National Interstate and Defense Highways Act.\nFor ten points, name this U.S. President who won the 1952 election with the slogan “I like Ike” after\nleading American troops in Europe in World War II.",
      "answer": [
        "Dwight David Eisenhower",
        "Dwight D. Eisenhower",
        "Eisenhower"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Neil Armstrong took a recording of theramin music and this man’s ninth symphony on Apollo 11. He\nwrote his twelfth string quartet while spending a summer in Spillville, Iowa, though his Slavonic Dances\nhonored Brahms and paid tribute to his native Bohemia. For ten points, name this Czech composer who,\nwhile visiting America, wrote his Symphony no. 9, “From the New World.”",
      "answer": [
        "Antonin Dvorak",
        "Dvorak"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "One artist from this country classified his work as “stabiles” and “mobiles,” one of which consists of\naluminum fins suspended on steel wire. That artist from this country, Alexander Calder, also created Bent\nPropeller, which was destroyed when the Minoru Yamasaki-designed World Trade Center was attacked on\n9/11. For ten points, name this country, home of the Museum of Modern Art in New York.",
      "answer": [
        "United States of America",
        "USA"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Supporters of this party were victims of the White Terror Massacre. The Xian [SHEE-ahn] incident\nwas perpetrated by members of this party. The Gang of Four consisted of members of this party and were\nlater found guilty of treason near the end of one of this party’s efforts, the Cultural Revolution. For ten\npoints, name this ruling party of an Asian nation once led by Mao Zedong.",
      "answer": [
        "Communist Party of China",
        "Chinese Coomunist Party",
        "China Communist",
        "Chinese Communist",
        "CCP"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This organization founded the Bowen Country Club as a summer camp. Toynbee Hall inspired this\ninstitution, which was founded on Halsted Street by Ellen Gates Starr and the first American woman to\nwin a Nobel Peace Prize. This organization started providing education and support to the poor in 1889.\nFor ten points, name this settlement house in Chicago co-founded by Jane Addams.",
      "answer": "Hull House"
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS QUESTION) Which U.S. President was investigated for his role in the Whitewater scandal and for an\naffair with Monica Lewinsky?",
      "answer": [
        "Bill Clinton",
        "Clinton"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country featured the highest scorer at the inaugural FIFA World Cup, Guillermo Stabile, whose\nteam lost to Uruguay in the finals. Mario Kempes led this country to a 1978 World Cup win as the host\nnation. In this country’s win over England at the 1986 World Cup, the “Hand of God” scored one goal\nfor Diego Maradona. For ten points, name this country whose soccer team, led by Lionel Messi, placed\nsecond in the 2014 World Cup.",
        "answer": "Argentina"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "In 2014, Messi won this award given to the World Cup’s best player. An annual award of the\nsame name is given by FIFA to the world’s best player.",
        "answer": [
          "Golden Ball",
          "Ballon d’Or"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nicholas Reeves has controversially suggested using radar in this location to find hidden rooms. Pierre\nLacau supervised a study of this location funded by Lord Carnavon who died of mosquito-borne disease\nshortly after it was opened. This location, officially designated KV62, was discovered in 1922 by Howard\nCarter. For ten points, name this surprisingly well-preserved burial site of a boy pharaoh.",
        "answer": [
          "the tomb of King Tutankhamun",
          "tomb Tut",
          "Crypt Tut",
          "Burial site Tut",
          "Tomb of Tutankhamun"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "King Tut’s tomb, like numerous other pharaoh tombs, was discovered in this Egyptian valley\nacross the Nile River from Thebes.",
        "answer": [
          "Valley of the Kings",
          "Kings"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Interahamwe engaged in one of these events after the death of Juvenal Habyarimana. Viktor\nYuschenko classified the Holodomor as one of these events, as the Soviets declared the possession of food\na crime. Turkey does not recognize one of these events against the Armenian people. For ten points, name\nthese atrocities that involve mass killings of a specific demographic, such as the Holocaust.",
        "answer": "genocide"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Holodomor was a massive famine in this former Soviet republic, which saw the Orange\nRevolution oust Viktor Yanukovych in favor of Victor Yushchenko in 2005.",
        "answer": "Ukraine"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Nobukazu Kuriki lost 9 fingers at this location in 2012, and a 1996 disaster here that killed Scott\nFischer was chronicled in Jon Krakauer’s Into Thin Air. No one summited this peak in 2015 after an April\nearthquake killed 19 people at its base camp and Nepal closed it for the season. The guide Tenzing Norgay\nand Sir Edmund Hillary were the first to climb, for ten points, what tallest mountain in the world?",
        "answer": [
          "Mount Everest",
          "Everest",
          "Sagarmatha",
          "Chomolungma"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Tenzing Norgay was a member of what Nepalese ethnic group, famous for guiding Himalayan\nmountain climbers?",
        "answer": "Sherpa"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "When asked about violence against followers of this religion, one politician responded, “When a big\ntree falls, the earth shakes.” An empire named for this religion ruled the Punjab under Maharaja Ranjit\nSingh during the first half of the 19th century. For ten points, name this monotheistic religion founded by\nGuru Nanak whose male adherents follow five articles of faith, including the keeping of uncut hair.",
        "answer": [
          "Sikhism",
          "Sikh"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Another article of Sikhism is the traditional possession of a kirpan, one of these items that, in\n2011, Quebec banned from governmental buildings.",
        "answer": [
          "ceremonial dagger",
          "dagger",
          "ceremonial sword",
          "sword"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man noted that “Our constitution does not copy the laws of neighboring states” in a speech\nthat offered “comfort [...], not condolence” after the first year of the Archidamian War. He evacuated the\nfarmers of Attica to within the Long Walls, which protected them from Spartan skirmishes but led to the\nspread of plague that killed him. For ten points, name this statesman of the Athenian Golden Age who\nopposed Sparta in the early Peloponnesian War.",
        "answer": "Pericles"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Pericles’ 431 BC oration commemorating the first year of the Peloponnesian War was given at\nwhat type of event?",
        "answer": "funeral"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "France briefly held Fort Caroline in what is now this state’s Timucuan Preserve. After the Seven\nYears’ War, this region was split into east and west sections at the Apalachicola River. The Adams-Onis\nTreaty ceded this region to the United States, which had been fighting the Seminoles in this territory\nand nearby Georgia. For ten points, name this once-Spanish territory, now a U.S. state with capital\nTallahassee.",
        "answer": [
          "Florida Territory",
          "Florida",
          "Spanish Florida"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Spanish explorer searched for the Fountain of Youth in Florida in 1513.",
        "answer": [
          "Juan Ponce de Leon",
          "Leon",
          "Ponce de Leon"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This country owns, but is not allowed to navigate, the western wetlands surrounding Lago Merin at\nthe delta of the Yaguaron River. Its western border is a river named for this country; that river combines\nwith the Parana River to form the Rio de la Plata. For ten points, name this country southwest of Brazil\nwhose capital is Montevideo.",
        "answer": "Uruguay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This country across the Uruguay River from Uruguay shares an agricultural region called the\nPampas with Uruguay, and also shares Patagonia with Chile.",
        "answer": "Argentina"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "AVIATION",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the last name of Orville and Wilbur, the builders of the first successful airplane?",
          "answer": [
            "Wright",
            "Wright Brothers"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first woman to fly solo non-stop across the Atlantic in 1932, but disappeared in the Pacific\nfive years later?",
          "answer": [
            "Amelia Earhart",
            "Earhart"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the nickname of German WWI ace Manfred von Richthofen?",
          "answer": "The Red Baron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first pilot to break the sound barrier?",
          "answer": [
            "Chuck Yeager",
            "Yeager"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the type of aircraft invented by the Montgolfier [mohn-GOAL-fee-ay] brothers in 1783?",
          "answer": "hot air balloon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the airplane that Charles Lindbergh flew for the first solo non-stop trans-Atlantic flight?",
          "answer": "The Spirit of St. Louis"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the Russian designer of the R-4 helicopter?",
          "answer": [
            "Igor Sikorsky",
            "Sikorsky"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the nickname of the H-4 Hercules, a flying boat designed by Howard Hughes?",
          "answer": "Spruce Goose"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "In the history of human flight, who or what..."
    },
    {
      "category": "EASTERN EUROPEAN COUNTRIES",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Unified the cities of Buda and Pest in 1873?",
          "answer": "Hungary"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was in a union with Montenegro until 2006?",
          "answer": "Serbia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Broke away from the Czech Republic in 1993?",
          "answer": "Slovakia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Had 7 border guards killed in a Soviet assault near Vilnius?",
          "answer": "Lithuania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is home to electrician, politician, and Nobel Peace Prize winner Lech Walesa [vah-WE-sa]?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the modern site of the former capital of the Kievan Rus?",
          "answer": "Ukraine"
        },
        {
          "question": "Saw its leader, Nicolae Ceausescu [CHO-ses-koo], executed for war crimes in a 1989 revolution?",
          "answer": "Romania"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was considered the “last dictatorship in Europe” under Alexander Lukashenko?",
          "answer": "Belarus"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Which Eastern European country..."
    },
    {
      "category": "MESOPOTAMIA",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Means “land between the rivers” in what ancient language spoken in Corinth and Athens?",
          "answer": [
            "Ancient Greek",
            "Greek"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the birthplace of what practice, including irrigation, that allowed hunter-gatherers to settle?",
          "answer": [
            "agriculture",
            "farm",
            "farming"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to the Hanging Gardens in what city?",
          "answer": "Babylon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Used what wedge-shaped form of writing?",
          "answer": "cuneiform"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the eastern part of a region known by what two-word term, named for its shape and arable land?",
          "answer": "Fertile Crescent"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was located between what two rivers that flow to the Persian Gulf?",
          "answer": [
            "Tigris and Euphrates Rivers",
            "Tigris and Euphrates"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Was primarily located in what modern-day country, whose cities include Mosul and Basra?",
          "answer": "Iraq"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was home to what city, whose Great Ziggurat was excavated by Leonard Woolley?",
          "answer": "Ur"
        }
      ],
      "prompt": "Mesopotamia..."
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Tral stations and the Command-Measurement Complex were used to observe this object.\nA part of this vehicle was derived from an R7 intercontinental ballistic missile, and it used (20 pts) ",
        "four radio antennas to broadcast a repeating, pulsing signal. President Eisenhower\ncreated ARPA and the government increased funding for (10 pts) ",
        "science and technology after this\nobject was launched in October 1957. The Soviets started the Space Race with the launch of, for ten\npoints, what first artificial satellite?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Sputnik I",
        "Sputnik"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man resigned one position after claiming the media wanted Donovan McNabb\nto do well because he is black. He offered to purchase aspirin for “all the (20 pts) ",
        "women at\nGeorgetown University” in response to Congressional testimony on birth control given by\nSandra (10 pts) ",
        "Fluke, who this man called a prostitute in 2012. For ten points, name this conservative\ncommentator whose talk-radio show is the most-listened-to radio program in the United States."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Rush Limbaugh",
        "Limbaugh"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man served as the defense lawyer for Samuel Houston after he assaulted fellow\ncongressman William Stanbury and later prosecuted the attempted assassin of Andrew\nJackson, Richard (20 pts) ",
        "Laurence. After boarding the HMS Tonnant, he witnessed the\nbombardment of Fort (10 pts) ",
        "McHenry and wrote a poem. For ten points, name this man whose Star\nSpangled Banner became the American national anthem."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Francis Scott Key",
        "Key"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One leader of this conflict, Jose Sanjurjo, died in a plane crash after leaving Estoril.\nThe term “Fifth Column” was coined during this war. The Abraham Lincoln Brigade was\none of the International Brigades to join this conflict, and (20 pts) ",
        "Nazi Germany supported\none side in this conflict with the Condor Legion. After seizing (10 pts) ",
        "Cartagena, Republican forces\nsurrendered to the Nationalists. For ten points, name this conflict in an Iberian country that brought\nFrancisco Franco to power."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Spanish Civil War",
        "Spanish Civil"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One mayor of this city, Abraham Beame, asked President Ford for a bailout in 1975.\nAnother mayor of this city drew criticism for limiting the size of (20 pts) ",
        "sugary soft drinks and\nfor his stop-and-frisk policy, the latter of which (10 pts) ",
        "Bill de Blasio campaigned against in 2013.\nMichael Bloomberg was a three-term mayor of, for ten points, what American city in which the police\npatrol Central Park and Times Square?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "New York City",
        "New York",
        "NYC"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this state, one state senator filibustered this state’s Senate Bill 5, which would have\nlimited access to abortions. That senator, Wendy Davis, lost in the 2014 gubernatorial\nelections for this state. The (20 pts) ",
        "presidential campaign of one Senator from this state\naroused controversy, as he was born in Canada; that senator is the first (10 pts) ",
        "Cuban-American\nto run for the presidency, Ted Cruz. For ten points, name this state whose current Governor, Greg Abbott,\nsucceeded the longest-serving governor in state history, Rick Perry."
      ],
      "answer": "Texas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man renounced his original citizenship in 1985 to legally become the owner of an\nAmerican TV station. He lured Sam Chisholm away from Kerry Packer’s Nine Network to\nbe the CEO of his company, (20 pts) ",
        "British Sky Broadcasting, and his conglomerate acquired\nthe Wall Street Journal in 2007. His tabloid, (10 pts) ",
        "News of the World, was shuttered in 2011 after\na celebrity phone hacking scandal. For ten points, name this founder of News Corp who, in 2015, stepped\ndown as CEO of 21st Century Fox."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Rupert Murdoch",
        "Murdoch"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man destroyed the Vandals after his generals won the battles of Tricamerum and\nAd Decimum. The Secret History by Procopius detailed the rule of this emperor and his\nmarriage to a (20 pts) ",
        "courtesan who convinced him to stay after a riot by the Blues and\nGreens. This survivor of the Nika Riots formed the (10 pts) ",
        "Corpus Juris Civilis, later known as his\nnamesake “Code.” For ten points, name this Byzantine emperor who built the Hagia Sophia."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Justinian the Great",
        "Justinian I"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) The Marquis of Pombal established the Douro Wine Company in this country. A\nsuccession crisis in this country was sparked after the death of (20 pts) ",
        "Sebastian I at the\nBattle of the Three Kings. It gained its independence from its eastern neighbor in the\nRestoration War. The House of (10 pts) ",
        "Braganza ruled, for ten points, what Iberian country\nthat colonized Brazil?"
      ],
      "answer": "Portugal"
    }
  ]
}